The Antarctic continent is the highest,
windiest,
driest and coldest continent in the
world. It contains around ninety percent
of the world's ice and thereby seventy percent of the
world's fresh water
and is home to giant active volcanoes
enormous subglacial lakes and rocks over
four billion years old
It is one of the few places in the world
that has never seen a war
where the environment is fully protected
and science has priority
The coast of Antarctica is dotted with
research stations from over 40 different countries
and is home to an international community
of scientists
some of whom are stationed on the
continent all year round
The interior of Antarctica is a vast
expanse of ice
in some places four kilometres thick. The
continent's divided in two by the Transantarctic mountains
high up on the polar plateau of east
antarctica
lies the South Pole, the goal of the
majority of tourism and expeditions that happens in the continent
It is the location of a giant US science base
These are the Ellsworth mountains in
West Antarctica
The highest mountain range in the whole
continent
They consist of the northern Sentinel
range and the Southern heritage range
The Heritage range is home to numerous
glaciers that flow down from the West Antarctic Plateau
One of which is called Union glacier, it is a large heavy crevassed glacier
86 kilometers long and nine kilometres
wide
and is the site and Union glacier camp
The camp is operated by Antarctic
Logistics and Expeditions
and is open for three months during the
Antarctic summer
It's situated near Union glacier blue ice runway
A naturally-occurring stretch of blue ice
ALE uses various types of aircraft
to operate in Antarctica
A large Russian Ilyushin jet runs
intercontinental flights from Chile
and transports the majority of heavy
cargo and passengers to the camp
A Bassler BT 67 and two de Havilland Twin Otters are used to fly within Antarctic
Both these aircraft are fitted with skis
and can land almost anywhere
For three months each year Union glacier
camp acts as a logistics hub for
scientists,
tourists,
South Pole teams,
and climbers
And ALE provide support to both private expeditions
and national Antarctic programs.
Every year movies are made, books written and stories
told of the expeditions that pass through the camp
This film is about the people who play a
part in making that possible
but in particular it is about the 10 people who
make up the Union glacier start-up crew
The start-up crew are a small team
that land in the pristine glacier ahead of
everybody else and a thousand kilometers from the nearest science base
It's their job to start setting up the
runway and camp for the season ahead
My name is Nigel Blancao I come from England
I work at Union glacier as a vehicle mechanic
My name's Ant. I'm the UG chef
I'm from England and this is the freezer
My name is Monica
I'm from Canada and I fly the Twin Otter
I'm Mike from Canada
I'm an aircraft maintenance
engineer eh
My name's Tom Weston I'm from the UK
my job is travel safety guide
Hi I'm Celine I'm from Ireland and my job
here is Comms operator
My name's Ian
I'm from North Yorkshire. My job here is
water, electricity and heating
Yo soy Boris. I am from Chile, Puenta Arenas Pacific.
My work here is
operator, mainly working in the blue-ice
runway.
My name is Al, from Yorkshire UK and my job is
mechanical services manager
And I'm Alex and I'm a copilot on the Twin Otter
The staff members change every season so
it's not always the same people flying in early
This year in addition to the 10 staff a
two-man expedition team that headed to the South Pole
has already passed through the camp
leaving the expedition manager
and filmmaker behind to get the first Ilyushin flight back to Chile
The weather is supposed to clear up the
next couple of days so until then
we've offered to help out with setting
up the rest of the camp
The blue ice runway is where the Ilyushin
lands and takes off
it's a hundred meters wide 3,000 meters
long
and the whole of Union glacier camp
exist because of this runway.
It's a rare section of ice that
doesn't accumulate new layers of snow each year
and as a result can take
and craft with much heavier loads.
the whole stretch a of ice has to be
cleared of snow before the Ilyushin can land
ALE have a large pair of
industrial snow blowers
but with strong winds blowing loose snow
down from the mountains almost every day, it's a difficult job
The weather in Antarctica can change quickly and dramatically
and blizzards can cause white-outs which
smother the campaign in almost zero visibility
These are four-season mountaineering tents
which are used by the staff
These double-walled clam tents are used for
clients and guests
This is the start-up tent which has
stayed on the ice all winter
It's heated by a stove and all the meals
for the start-up crew are served here
This is one of several vehicles which
stays on the glacier all year round
These are four Ski-Doos
This is the Twin Otter. The plane that flew the first staff members onto the ice
It has a crew of three and is operated by
Kenn Borek Air
These are washing lines for drying
clothes
These are drums of aviation fuel
which nearly everything in the camp runs
on
This is the Comms box, the communications hub of the camp
It's situated next to a large radio mast to improve signal
These are the toilets. There are separate ones for men and women
and aren't particularly warm at all
Most things in camp are within walking distance,
but in bad weather it's often easier to
use a Ski-Doo to get around
Antarctica may hold the record for the
coldest temperature ever recorded,
but right now it's approaching the
Antarctic summer
so the climate is comparatively mild.
Sometimes when the skies are clear
and the wind dies down, you can get away
with being outside in just a couple of thin layers
The staff call this a Dingle Day.
But this season winter temperatures are
lingering and working outside can still be a challenge
Right now the temperatures minus 25
degrees Celsius
A lovely day sitting on the porch
enjoying the weather and the beautiful view
That's my favorite
Yeah the weather is definitely spot-on
here
The weather doesn't really affect me because I've got a nice warm cab to drive around in
All I have to do is turn the heat up a little bit
Seems to affect everyone else with their hats on and coats. Looks very cold out there
It's about minus 25
degrees centigrade at the moment
The wind is blowing probably 20-25 knots.
Probably about -40 wind-chill. You definitely want something on the end of these when you're working outside
It takes a couple days to get used to it
after I having a summer back in Canada
but a couple of days and it feels like normal
Not too bad, I'm from the North, I'm alright
You've got loads of gear on, just wrap up warm
When you can go inside it's great
I have four layers on top, two layers
on the bottom
One, two, three, four, five
Five on my top. And two on my legs
On my head I have my toque. My toque and my hood
Balaclava, woolly hat, hood, goggles
Pull it down over your face
it gives your face some sort of protection against the wind
which really bothers my
cheeks and nose. And then put a hat on top which keeps your head warm
Most of the staff have boots rated for use in temperatures as low as minus a hundred degrees Celsius
Despite their warmth they still need
regular drying out in front of the stove
to stop sweat freezing to the boots'
insulation layers.
This is the freezer. It's a shipping
container that has been sunk into the ice
and is accessible by makeshift shaft.
It contains all of the frozen food that has
been left in storage whilst the campus
closed during the winter
The start-up crew bring a few supplies with
them from Chile
but the majority food stocks will arrive
with the first Ilyushin flight
So until then Ant has to work with
whatever he can find here
I found a Beef Fillet!
Probably the biggest thing I do at
the moment is making water
Cooking, cleaning, washing-up.
Basically just feeding the start-up crew.
Breakfast, lunch and dinner
Kind of just giving them as varying meals as I can think of with what I've got
Ant cooks three hot meals a day,
but the crew can also have snacks in
between. This is a tube of Kryzpos
They're a Chilean brand potato chips known
by the staff as crazy-poos
There's also lots of wine
to go with the evening meal
but nobody will recommend it much. The
most important is that the chef
is fantastic. He's his marvelous, always making the
food here so I am very very happy with
everything working in the kitchen.
Well, the food is fantastic
It shows
Just excellent
The food is excellent, Ant is a Super Chef
Breakfast, lunch and dinner.
Really? That's really nice, isn't it? That's really nice of them
Flags are used to mark where
the main road runs through the camp
The camp covers a sizeable area of the glacier
And the staff use a multitude of vehicles to to move equipment and travel from one part to another
This is a Ski-Doo
Nigel will tell you what everything else is because he's much more qualified
ALE have a fleet of these wheel vans they are on low gappage tires
Which enables them to drive over the snow. We mainly use them to ferry clients from the blue ice runway back to camp
But we do use them occasionally to get out and about and do some expedition work locally
This is a Tucker Snow Cat. It's four
wheel drive, it's on tracks
We use it around camp as a general work horse. It's got a blade on the front so we can bulldoze snow and groom areas
It can tow implements and groom surfaces
It carry cargo in the back, and also again, it goes out on exhibitions locally
This is a Prinoth BR 350 snow groomer.
We use it as a snow groomer around camp
and down at the blue ice runway
We also use it as a traverse tractor
which enables us to tow about forty tonnes of cargo out into the field
We use that as fuel laying depots for our planes or on science expeditions
Favourite? I'd go for the BR
I's just more adaptable, it can do more things
The comms box is also the hub for all
weather information
Meteorologists use the data gathered
from automatic weather stations down on the blue ice runway
and compare them with satellite imagery to
provide wind and weather updates to flight crews
climbers and expeditions on the ice.
Everyday Celine receives a new weather update
it's the same weather information
the crew of the Ilyushin are using in Chile
For the first flight of the season
the pilot won't fly unless the
conditions are perfect
He needs good visibility
good contrast
and low wind speeds
and he also won't want the Sun in his eyes when approaching the runway
Which rules out a night flight
This weather window must last for the time it
takes to fly from Chile to Union glacier and back again
and include the time it
takes to unload and reload any cargo
About a 12-hour round-trip
There's already a sweepstake amongst the
crew as to when it will land
3:30 on November 3rd
p.m.
I guess it could be another at least
three days
No comment
sorry
During an average season
Union glacier camp can expect around 350
to 450 visitors
The camp can house just over 100 people
at any time
and is made of a PolarHaven tents most
of them need to be assembled from scratch
but a few left intact over winter these
need to be dug out
and shifted into the right position
Until the weather improves
there will be no fresh food deliveries
and the camp will need to be set-up
by just the twelve people on the ice
So to put one of these big tents up, first
we have to level the snow
then we lay the floorboards, join them all
together
attach the frames, bolt that down
and then the big covers go on
and they're a multi-person job
tie them down and put the windows in, and
there we have it, a lovely
tent in Antarctica
Each of the PolarHaven tents are heated
by large stoves that runs on aviation fuel
And each tent connected to a solar panel
outside that
provides electricity for the staff and clients
these panels also supply energy to the snow melters in order to make hot water for cooking
And to strengthen the tents against strong winds
deep holes are drilled into the snow to secure guide ropes
This one's the dining tent it's gonna
attach onto the kitchen
and it'll feed about a hundred people when it's full
I quite like washing-up
What's wrong with it Tom? It's dead!
Can you fix it?
I know a man who can
Who's that?
Best part of the job is fixing things and
sense of achievement. The downside
of the job is probably having to go
outside in the cold
and things generally breakdown in the
worst weather conditions
The worst thing about the job is
just missing family and friends at home
The staff can use satellite phones to call
people back home,
but it can be costly
and it's cheaper to send an email
I'm gonna be here for four months this
time
and missing Christmas and missing my family
Ian's birthday is at the beginning of the season
so as well as Christmas and New Year,
he spends it working at Union glacier
Happy Birthday Ian!
Thank you Tom
It's curious to know what he might want for
present
down here, in Antarctica
Dancing girls!
Well he likes ice cream as well
But I haven't got any egg yolks
Happy Birthday. That's yours, that one is yours
Anty made me a cake
The 3 rules of Ski-Dooing are:
Always drive when you can see
Attach yourself with the kill-corde,
and never drink and drive, kids!
The 3 rules of riding in a sled are:
Never exit a moving vehicle
Keep your hands and feet in at all times
And trust your driver!
During the Antarctic summer the Sun
never sets on Union glacier
it just skirts the horizon sometimes
ducking behind the mountains
but always providing enough light so the
staff never have to use a torch in their tents
When the wind picks up
it blows snow off the nearby mountain
tops. It takes a short while,
but eventually the wind reaches the camp
itself
As it advances, it creates a whirl of loose fine grain snow like a soft mist flowing over the glacier's surface
It is known as spindrift
Late at night when the Sun is low in the
sky and lighting the mountain ridges from behind,
the snow roles gently off the slopes
of the high peaks and down into camp
It is one of the most beautiful sites
that can be seen in Antarctica
Here's the latest weather report: snow, and cold.
For some of the start-up crew
this is their third or fourth season working
in Antarctica. Amongst the team
Nigel holds the longest record for being
on the continent
an impressive 24 seasons some are from
over summer
and some over winter. Sometimes for an
entire year straight through
it adds up to a total of over nine years.
I think the Ilyushin is going to land on... Friday
Tomorrow, no Friday, yeap
Friday
Friday I reckon
While some of the crew thinking about the
delayed plane or maybe being at home
Boris has imagined an entire planet
that he can escape to
He calls at Planet Boris
So, Planet Boris, what's happening on Planet Boris today?
All right, now that the weather's cleared up a bit and the wind's died down
I thought I'd give you a quick tour of the Twin Otter
This is a de Havilland Twin Otter series 300 that is currently on board skis
This is the left propeller. This is
the inside of the Twin Otter
Contrary to popular belief these are not my training wheels
These are full drums of jet-fuel that we tie to the wings
for days like today when the wind
is blowing pretty hard
We have Bush-Style seats, which fold-down
This is the tail-section
We can take 19 passengers and we have
about four and a half hours range
without our fairy tanks
this is the right propeller
Nose cone
This is the cockpit of our Twin Otter
I forget the number but there's like 500
pounds, no not even
Hold on, erase that part. This much
Pogo Stick
The Twin Otter can be outfitted with, Floats, Wheels, Wheel-Skis and Board-Skis
The most common load is about
3,000 to 4,000 pounds of freight or people
We generally work in Antarctica on
Board-Skis that can land in
just about anywhere on the continent, but other than that it's pretty standard stuff
And that cocludes the tour of the Twin Otter. Stay classy Antarctica.
To stay in touch with each other everyone
carries one of these VHF handheld radios
It can be used around base, on the runway and in some of the vehicles
Boris, Boris, Tom.
Tom, Tom, Tom, Boris.
Ah, Boris yes. What is a Donkey with three legs?
Dunno
Wonky.
When the clouds around camp clear you
can see the huge mountain ranges that
surround Union glacier
Though not visible from the camp itself
it is only 150 kilometers to the foot
of Mt. Vincent
the highest mountain in Antarctica
which people come from all over the
world to climb
Monica will now point out some other
noteworthy peaks
These the Enterprise hills
This is Mt. Rossman
That tall peak there is Mt. Dolence, which is the highest peak in that range
Just in front of that is the Connell canyon
Out in the distance you'll see elephant's head. When we have better visibility you can see the shape of an elephant's head
We're hear at Union glacier camp. Elephant's head is down here
Parts of the ice that makeup Union glacier believed to be a hundred and eighty thousand years old
It is recommended by some of the staff as
the perfect accompaniment to glass of scotch
Coming in after a really cold day and
having a cup of tea that's probably the best bit
Waking up in the morning with frost on your sleeping-bag,
isn't so great, but it's quite amusing at the same time
I can imagine the guys with longer beards.
you know I wonder if ever get stuck to their sleeping bag
I think it does, I think it gives a little bit of a buffer
you don't have to
worry too much about the wind burn on
half the face
It ices up a bit when you get some wind
Overall, I feel it makes me a bit warmer
Polar wisdom has been a mixed affair
regarding beards
The icons of the Heroic Age of Antarctic
exploration were almost all bearded
and it's an image that many modern-day
explorers model themselves on
Whilst on expeditions Ernest Shackleton and Captain Falcon Scott championed large frost-encrusted beards,
whilst the Norwegian explorer Roald Amundsen
famously preferred a closely-trimmed look or even clean-shaven
he wrote in his journal: "a beard in the
polar regions
seems to me to be just as awkward and
unpractical
as walking with a tall hat on each foot."
Well, I haven't shaved in about
10 years, but I do trim
This length is probably about four or five months worth of growth
maybe a bit more
There's Myself
Alex
Boris
Tom
Ian
Nigel
I don't think...
I don't think Al has one, he's the only one
without one.
Boris, Boris. Tom.
Um, yes Tom.
What do you call a donkey,
with three legs and one eye?
Winky Wonky
These are the fuel drums behind the
toilets
all human excrement in Antarctica has to
be removed and flown off the continent
as a result staff and clients sometimes
end up accompanying their own waste back to Chile during the flight home
The forecast
is still not good enough for the Ilyushin flight
but the Twin Otters can fly in the short
windows of better weather
There are no clients to ferry around
but fuel depots can be laid on the ice
for use later in the season
It's difficult not to be envious of the
flight crew, they get to travel around
the entire continent
and in doing so see some the best views
in Antarctica and there are many places on the map they won't fly
Union glacier is here in the Heritage Range
We fly clients around to
different
destinations for instance the South Pole
The South Pole
we take climbers to Mt. Vincent Massif base camp, and they climb
Mt. Vincent is just over here
We take people to see the Penguins out in Gold Bay
and Gold Bay where people go to the Emporer Penguin camp
Those are some of the jobs we do here for ALE
Tom's GPS dance consists of:
swaying your hips while keeping a GPS steady hanging around your neck
I don't know
I can't explain it
It's a Tom-ism
Let's not ever do that again, please
Operation Time Machine
A top secret mission to fool the chef
into cooking lunch earlier than neccesary
It worked! He was very confused
What day is it today?
Due to the delayed plane
and the fairly mundane wine
We are creating port, by distilling the wine
by the natural process of freezing
and now centrifuging the alcohol and liquids
out of the ice to make it stronger
In 1959 representatives from a dozen
countries including the US and Russia
met in Washington to sign the Antarctic
Treaty it was an agreement that would make Antarctica free of weapons
keeping the continent reserved for
Scientific Research only
All the signatories vow to refrain from
making any claims to territory
today there are fifty states party
to the treaty
and in 1998 a protocol on
Environmental Protection came into force
It banned all commercial mining and
designated the whole continent as a nature reserve
Never before or since have nations agreed
to such a comprehensive and firm set of rules
to protect the environment have such a
large part of the world
Since the treaty was signed
investigations have been made into Antarctica's resources
Some suspect it to be the home of the
third largest oil reserve in the world
An estimated $200 billion barrels of oil
This oil is extremely difficult and at
the moment prohibitively expensive to extract
but in 2048 when the Antarctic
Treaty is open for review
and when drilling and mining techniques
may be more advanced
It is widely considered that the
long-standing ban on this practice will come to an end
and much like the warming Arctic north
there is a rush of human activity
to secure these possible reserves
In a world hungry for dwindling fossil
fuels
fresh water scarcity and soaring
energy needs
The very countries that signed the
Antarctic Treaty are spending lavishly to
explore the potential
on the world's last unexpoited continent
when a new Antarctic Treaty is drawn up
it will change the continent and the way we see it forever
Antarctica has been free of conflict and aggression
in a way that other parts of the world
have always desired. It has been a shelter for knowledge
and the attempt to understand the
changing planet we live on
It has also been a land of myth, of heroic
deeds and struggles
despite being so remote, so barren and
stark
It has become entangled in the search for
individual meaning and self-knowledge
amidst a fetish for exploration and
discovery
people have come to Antarctica to seek their nobility in the ice
And soon when it is seen only as a resource it will no longer give us meaning or knowledge
It will become just another part of the
globe, another asset rich territory
indistinguishable in all but appearance
from the rest of the world
that we sought to protect it from
The first Ilyushin flight has been
delayed by three weeks due to the bad weather
It has delayed the rest to the camp staff
from arriving
and also trapped Andy and I from
flying home
but when it does finally arrive,
regardless how exciting it may appear
it will be sad to leave
The best part of working in Anarctica is probably the close-knit team that we
have around here
Everybody seems to see things as the same goal, so when things go wrong
everybody just gets to it and generally gets the job done
Fine, easy we're all pretty much like-minded people who want to be here
It's one of the most stunning places in the world
It is probably the most beautiful place
I fly
Other than the Arctic. There are
close seconds for sure
but it's such a vast and beautiful,
beautiful, spot to be and see. I feel
very fortunate that
I get paid to see all these places that
others,
don't usually get a chance in their lifetime to see.
It's a really cool place
and you get to climb some mountains which have never been climbed before
and to work with some cool people
Every time I get up out of my tent it might be freezing cold, but I'm happy to be here.
Yeah, it's nice
Cameraman: And what's the best part of being in Antarctica and working here?
Well, point your camera out the window and have a look
Andy, what has been your most memorable
moment in the three weeks you've spent here?
When I was told the Ilyushin's coming
What are you most looking forward to?
Maybe a beer
I dunno, I'm gonna miss you guys
about four hours
when the Ilyushin lands all the food,
fuel and other supplies for the camp will
be taken off the plane
and then it will be reloaded with waste
material for the return flight to Chile
The pilot will stay on the runway
for just two hours
so it'll be a very quick turnaround
It's a four and a half hour flight from Chile
and even though it could change
unexpectedly, the weather conditions are looking good
On-board the Ilyushin, looking through
the starboard window
and if the time of day is right, the moon
is visible hanging low in the sky
It drifts slowly up and down as the
aircraft passes through gentle winds in the atmosphere
The feeling of leaving antarctica
is though it was a cold distant moon or some other Frozen Planet
and it is a struggle to make sense and
of what it will mean
to get back home
Evening
This is my tent, this is where I'll be sleeping for the next three months
And this is the view I'll be looking at, it's amazing
The tag's got comfort -29
the limit of comfort -40
and extreme -67, allegedly
I quite like it when it's windy, it's
like the tack on a sail, you can hear the
the tack clanging against the mast. I like to hear the tent
rattling around me. And I'm all wrapped up thinking: yeah I'm well cozy